George Alexander Louis Lebour Papers 1852-1914 Mss.B.L491
American Philosophical Society
George Alexander Louis Lebour Papers
1852-1914
Mss.B.L491
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
Geologist George Alexander Louis Lebour was a minor figure in nineteenth century England. Educated at the Royal School of Mines, Lebour served as Professor of Geology at Durham College of Science and then Vice-Principal of Armstrong College, formerly Durham College of Science and presently University of Newcastle-upon-Tyne. He was most associated with his publication on the geology of Durham and Northumberland and he wrote more then 100 papers mainly on carboniferous geology, heat-conductivity of rocks, and the transfer of heat through the earth's crust. The Lebour Papers are comprised of 0.25 linear feet of correspondence relating to Lebour's interest in the analysis and sharing of geological specimens, geological surveying, and underground temperatures. There are a few letters with the Geological Society of London and with Richard Howse, the curator of the Natural History museum of Newcastle-upon-Tyne regarding the loaning of specimens.
Lebour, George Alexander Louis, 1847-1918
Bibliography
There is a obituary in Geological Magazine 5 (1918): 287-288.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Accessioned, 1980 (accn. no. 1980-848ms).
Scope and Contents note
This relatively small collection contains incoming correspondence of Lebour and correspondence between other individuals including Walter Calverley Trevelyan, William Crawford Williamson, Hanns Bruno Geinitz and G. J. Symons. The correspondence primarily relates to the exchange and analysis of geological specimens. There are some correspondences of Richard Howse, then curator of the Natural History Museum of Newcastle-upon-Tyne regarding the exchange of fossil specimens. Also included are a few letters to the Geological Society requesting information or copies of publications.
Biographical/Historical note
George Alexander Louis Lebour was born in 1847 and educated at the Royal School of Mines. Little else is know of his early life. At the age of 20 Lebour began to serve on the Geological Survey of England. Using the knowledge he gained from that eight-year experience he accepted a position as lecturer of geological surveying at the University of Durham College of Science in Newcastle from 1973 to 1879, and succeeded Dr. David Page as Professor of Geology, a position he occupied until his death.
Lebour may have been most noted for his work on the geology of Northumberland and Durham. He wrote the "The Geology of Durham" published in the Handbook to the Geology and Natural History of Northumberland and Durham. Of his many other papers on the geology of Durham most notable are those dealing with the classification of the Salt-measures, the breccia-filled fissures in the Magnesian Limestons, and the Marl Slate and Yellow Sands. Throughout his professional career Lebour was most concerned with the transfer of heat through the earth's crust and the determination of the thermal conductivity of rocks. His findings publishing in a series of British Association reports from 1873 to 1881 were accepted as the standard of the time.
Bonney, T. G., (Thomas George), 1833-1923; Cole,William Willoughby, 3rd Earl of Enniskillen, 1807-1886; Davidson, Thomas, 1817-1885; Dewalque, G., (Gustave), 1826-1905; Geikie, Archibald, Sir, 1835-1924; Geikie, James, 1839-1915; Geinitz, Hanns Bruno, 1814-1900; Geological Society of London; Gilbert, Grove Karl, 1843-1918; Howorth, Henry H., Sir, (Henry Hoyle), 1842-1923; Howse, Richard; Lapparent, Albert Auguste Cochon de, 1839-1908; Natural History Museum (Newcastle-upon-Tyne); Oliver, Daniel, 1830-1916; Ramsay, Wilhelm, 1865-1928; Renevier, Eugene, 1831-1906; Roemer, Ferdinand, 1818-1891; Symons, G. J., (George James), 1838-1900; Thornbill, John; Trevelyan, Walter Calverley, Sir, 1797-1879; Watson, Robert Spence, 1837-1911; Williamson, William Crawford, 1816-1895; Geology; Specimens.
- George Alexander Louis Lebour Papers, 1852-1914; 0.25 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - ALS to Richard Howse, 1852 October 8; 1p.; Thornbill, John
  - ALS to [?], 1860 July 31; 3p.; [Bathwith], Robert
  - ALS to [Richard] Howse, 1862 January 12; 1p.; Charlton, Edward
  - ALS to [Richard] Howse, 1871 August 24; 1p.; Earl of Enniskillen
  - ALS to [Richard] Howse, 1872 July 25; 1p.; Kirkby, James W.
  - ALS to, 1875 December 4; 2p.; Oliver, D[aniel], 1830-1916
  - ALS to Richard Howse, 1876 October 24; 2p.; Roemer, Ferdinand, 1818-1891
  - ALS to [?], 1876 December 8; 2p.; Egerton, M. Grey
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1877 December 23; 2p.; Trevelyan, Walter Calverley, Sir, 1797-1879
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1879 April 16; 1p.; Nebey, E
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1881 March 22; 2p.; Brown, J.[M.]
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1881 March 22; 3p.; Williamson, William Crawford, 1816-1895
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1881 July 8; 2p.; Trevelyan, Walter Calverley, Sir, 1797-1879
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1887 April 8; 3p.; [Hayes, L. McKenny]
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1887 June 5; 2p.; Williamson, William Crawford, 1816-1895
  - ALS to [George Alexander Louis Lebour], 1890 October 14; 2p.; Tomlinson, William W.
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1891 October 19; 2p.; Symons, G. J., (George James), 1838-1900
  - ANS to the Geological Society of London, 1892 February 12; 1p.; Geinitz, Hanns Bruno, 1814-1900
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1893 April 27; 2p.; Gilbert, Grove Karl, 1843-1918
  - ANS to Geological Society of London, 1893 July 5; 1p.; Berkeley, Earl of
  - ALS to [George Alexander Louis Lebour], 1894 June 12; 2p.; Bonney, T. G., (Thomas George), 1833-1923
  - ANS to Belinfante, L. L., 1897 April 22; 1p.; Renevier, Eugene, 1831-1906
  - ANS to Belinfante, L. L., 1898 March 8; 1p.; Lapparent, Albert Auguste Cochon de, 1839-1908
  - ANS to Geological Society of London, 1898 March 12; 1p.; Geinitz, Hanns Bruno, 1814-1900
  - ANS to Geological Society of London, 1898 July 4; 1p.; Dewalque, G., (Gustave), 1826-1905
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1898 August 25; 3p.; Howorth, Henry H., Sir, (Henry Hoyle), 1842-1923
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1898 January 8; 3p.; Ellean, John
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1902 January 22; 3p.; Lapworth, Charles, 1842-1920
  - ANS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1903 July 11; 1p.; Geikie, Archibald, Sir, 1835-1924
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1907 July 5; 1p.; Watson, Robert Spence, 1837-1911
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1912 September 26; 3p.; Geikie, James, 1839-1915
  - ALS to George Alexander Louis Lebour, 1914 June 22; 2p.; Ramsay, Wilhelm, 1865-1928
  - ALS to [George Alexander Louis Lebour], 4p.; Davidson, Thomas, 1817-1885
  - ALS to [Richard] Howse, n.d.; 2p.; Salter, John William, 1820-1869